hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream
81.1 it is April 23rd or 24th depending
on where you are and we're here with
Hannah Bedell discussing feeling our way
through uncertainty thank you for
joining Hannah we'll have a presentation
followed by a discussion second
so looking forward to anyone's questions
in the live chat and thanks again for
joining and looking forward to it thanks
so much Daniel I'm really looking
forward to it too um like I said before
been a big fan of the YouTube channel
for a long time so it's really nice to
be here um so today I'm going to talk
about uh some of my work in my PhD uh
which is about arousal coherence um
which will make more sense in a moment
the basic uh topic is how we might feel
our way through
uncertainty through the link between
affect and
interception uh
so me one
minute all right so I'm going to be
talking about uh this
paper that I wrote with
Mark Helen slaga and Ruben linan so in
um Neuroscience of Consciousness
recently uh and we'll talk about it kind
of Step by Step um I will note at the
get-go that there's no formal modeling
yet for this concept so this talk and
the paper um is basically a series of
claims um which I kind of back up with
other people's experiments models and
simulations so I'm just piecing together
some prior ideas basically and looking
at where those might lead um in
particular interceptive self- inference
deep affective inference uh and excuse
me um AFF in terms of precision
optimization and if those aren't clear
yet they might be soon hopefully uh
so these are the basic claims that I'm
going to make
and it's going to be quite a quick talk
because there's only five so firstly
that your autonomic arousal States track
with changes and uncertainty and that
means multiple things um I'll break down
uh some of those in the next
slide uh that accurately inferring
autonomic arousal is important for the
way that our brains estimate
uncertainty and that effective arousal
um might
optimize the way that how confident we
are in autonomic prediction errors so
it's going to effective arousal will
also impact potentially the accuracy of
our interceptive autonomic
inferences um which will lead me to the
kind of point of the paper which is
arousal coherence so that
is uh you can kind of see here this is a
very simple depiction oversimplified
depiction of what arousal coherence
would look like so we have changes in
autonomic arousal across time increases
and decreases coherent effective arousal
would be changing with the autonomic
arousal and disc
coherent effec of arousal would be
dissociated from changes in autonomic
arousal and it is not very simple
obviously um there layers of depth to
change so the simple time axis is an
oversimplification but this is a basic
idea of arousal coherence and I think
and have argued in this paper that it
impacts and reflects our capacity to
adapt to changes in
uncertainty um of multiple different
kinds and uh final point is meta
awareness of arousal so knowing your
arousal or having a higher order
representation of of your arousal I
might enhance arousal coherence and I'll
talk about some of the benefits
associated with higher arousal coherence
to
um just quickly to mention the way that
I am conceiving effec of arousal is a
lower order uh prediction so it's not
the same as emotion um like stress
anxiety excitement but
uh High arousal is common across those
kinds of emotions whereas a relaxing
state for instance would be a low
arousal and if I we're talking about
autonomic arousal um I'd like to clarify
that I'm not being very specific here
about whether we're talking about
sympathetic arousal sympathetic
activation or parasympathetic or the
balance between those just broadly
increases of autonomic arousal or
decreases um conceived through things
like heart rate increase or changes in
pupil
dilation
um
okay so
um I I have not included as yet a uh a
primer on active inference given the
audience and given the channel um basic
concepts uh would be that I'm conceiving
of action and perception as
inferences um in a loop kind of
inseparable um also looking at
inferences as deep so uh one layer of
inference H can be nested within other
layers of inference and that will come
up especially as we start talking about
aect and a third concept from the active
literature is the idea of precision as
an inverse uncertainty estimate and so
confidence in signals or confidence in
beliefs um so if anything that is is
unclear about what I'm talking about
especially with these terms please just
jump right
in um and I also just want to take this
chance to say if anyone wants to talk
about formal modeling please let me know
offline I'd love to talk about it
um okay so I'm just going to dive
straight into the first claim unless
there's any questions
Daniel cool first
claim pretty simple um autonomic States
track with changes and uncertainty
there's a number of different um lines
of evidence that support this and they
date back quite a while um the work of
um Y and Dian comes to mind in
particular
there was a lot of work in the early
2000s where they looked at different
neurom modulators of autonomic arousal
um in
particular adrenaline or neurop
nephrine and changes in pupil dilation
that relate to that that track with
changes in
uncertainty uh we can also talk about
their changes in volatility changes in
Surprise violations
of precise expectations so we see these
embodied changes
in response to small changes in
environment in uncertainty in the
environment um I won't call it
environmental uncertainty because it's
not necessarily precise uh one of my
favorite papers in this area was by
debka and his colleagues at
UCL and they had a task a probabilistic
learning task uh so two rocks under one
of the Rocks there's a snake if there's
a snake you get an electric
shock and uh they manipulated the
probability that each Rock would have a
snake underneath it and looked at people
whether people were able to
learn the associations as those
associations changed over the course of
the experiment and they found that
people whose autonomic arousal responses
changed with the irreducible uncertainty
uh we're better able to learn those
probabilistic relationships so it's not
as simple as this is some epiphenomena
or the the way that your body tracks
with changes and uncertainty seems to
have very
important impacts on how well you track
uncertainty and how well you can use
that information another piece of
evidence there is that um I can't
remember the chemicals name there f
propol I think is the name of it um
suppressing your autonomic arousal
responses so your pupilary and cardiac
arousal reduces learning when the
environment changes so you you it looks
like the effects of Prior beliefs
increases so you're not updating your
uncertainty as well when you don't have
these embodied
changes um that track with
uncertainty so that's the first claim
there autonomic arousal States track
with changes and uncertainty and it
matters that they
do second claim is that inferring our
autonomic arousal States
informs uncertainty
estimates so here I'm drawing pretty
heavily on the work of mik Allen
I really enjoy this interceptive self-
inference idea um which is
that by inferring our autonomic arousal
States we can better estimate changes in
expected
uncertainty
so at the simplest level things like
your heartbeat come with changes in
sensory noise so um for example you get
pulsatile blood flow across your retina
and you can't
see in that instance as well so by
anticipating those changes in your
heartbeat uh the brain can or by
intercep self- inferring them the brain
can
adjust expected Precision
accordingly um and then we can extend
that
to uh different layers of temporal depth
so if your heartbeat is going to impact
Precision then your heart rate over time
will also have some impact on
uncertainty there um by extension so
there's different levels when we're
talking about autonomic States um in
terms of the actual State and then we
have rhythms and
Etc
um another interesting thing to note
with this idea of interceptive self-
inference is that if the brain can infer
these expected States uh it can likely
also
control uh these states so using the
body to control Precision
trajectories so um depending on uh the
contextual need in the
environment the body can change
depending on uncertainty so so we saw
some indication of this in the previous
slide these changes where the body is
tracking with uncertainty maybe
operating through a basic inactive
interceptive self- inference another
example is that um with perceptual
uncertainty your heart rate
slows um which
increases the amount of time and
predictability um
of the diol aspect of your heart
beat and therefore um High
predictability
of and opportunities for high Precision
sensory sampling so
uh anyway that's interceptive self-
inference um I think it's a fantastic
idea and I want to basically with this
just just layer up and look at
um what might be impacting
interceptive self- inference and in
particular interceptive
Precision
so to in order to infer these
interceptive
conditions uh we need to be able to
adapt interceptive Precision when things
change so typically interceptive
Precision would be considered quite High
you have a lot of homeostatic states
that you need to stay in you need your
heartbeat within a certain range in
order to survive for
example but things do change and you
need to be able to adapt how confident
you are in your interceptive beliefs and
interceptive errors and this seems to
have pretty big implications for health
so um Ryan Smith's
work recently on this I found really
interesting um they
gave people
a uh heartbeat tapping task um so just
trying to detect their heartbeat during
um interceptive perturbation so holding
their
breath
and their modeling showed that where
healthy individuals change their
interceptive Precision when things
change um people with an symptoms of
anxiety depression substance disorders
and eating disorders didn't change their
Precision estimates from resting
levels
okay
so uh
that's claim two we can use autonomic
states to inform our uncertainty
estimates claim
three and this is
a based on a kind of just adult of work
in affective inference so there's a lot
of people
uh working on veillance in this area and
I've seen some really beautiful work and
in particular I I really like um Casper
hesp at Al's paper on this um
considering higher order or affect
as a deeper or
a um TR to think the opposite of
nested an embedding of lower order
inferences
so representing changes in lower level
uncertainty at a higher level as a kind
of abstraction and that is what
affect is
uh we can talk more about the specifics
of veillance after but um the key that I
want to draw attention to here is that
uh deviations in this uncertainty a
lower level uncertainty or lower level
errors some people call it some people
talk about specifically interceptive
errors some people talk about
homeostatic errors regardless the just
Del is that people are talking about
changes or unexpected deviations
ascending from that lower level to a
higher level of effective inference and
that's where arousal seems to be key so
it's an orienting
towards signals that are expected to
resolve future
uncertainty this links in nicely with um
some old ideas I know SS and fit priston
referred to them earlier um faf in 2006
talks about cortical arousal and
Information Gain there's also a really
nice research group uh Yana sagala in
Japan who talks about uh effective
arousal of
stimuli relating to novelty and
Information Gain obeys the Enterprise so
there's a pretty
consistent IDE here
that arousal is relating to orienting
towards valuable
information akin to uh attentional
selection but more specific to effective
information um and a final piece here is
a lovely
study um by Candia Rivera and colleagues
um um and they looked at heart brain
coupling during emotional experiences
it's another reason I'm thinking
affective arousal in particular is
important for
optimizing interceptive
precision and they had people undergo
emotional elicitation watching videos
and within the first few seconds they
found that the emotional stimuli were
modulating or activating heartbeat
activity
which in
turn uh led to kind of arousal specific
cortical response and then there was a
bidirectional processing which is what
we kind of know about emotions affect in
the body right it's
bidirectional but the key thing here for
me was that the afferent information
from the body to the brain in that
coupling that information flow was
modulated by asec of arousal particular
uh and not bance or anything else
so how aroused you said you
felt was modulating how much information
was kind of coming up to your brain from
your
body after the initial kind of
activation um thank you
doie apologize this one's a bit text
Heavy um but we're almost at the end so
uh this is where arousal coherence comes
in again the relationship between or
correlation between autonomic arousal
and affective arousal within a person
across
time
um
so
uh recapping a little bit if
affective States recruit bodily signals
or or specifically the outcomes of
interceptive inferences errors or not um
to model the current Estates of Affairs
and changes in autonomic
arousal reflect an enact changes in
uncertainty and
precision then affective arousal I'm
suggesting might reflect this minimally
metacognitive to to quote p a
mechanism through which the Precision of
interceptive self inference can
be regulated and represented at a
conscious
level and I think that this is important
and ties back potentially to the work
with uh Ryan Smith and this um I think
that's
the this page here so the failure to
adapt inter receptive Precision in
response to autonomic
changes I think this is where uh
effective arousal comes in and this
coherence is the capacity to
adapt into receptive Precision according
to changes in autonomic States and I
think based on
the relationship between autonomic
arousal and uncertainty then that
arousal coherence might shape the
responsiveness especially at this uh
conscious level to changing levels of
uncertainty so through the body in into
the
environment um and then if we
can monitor and track the changing
uncertainty then we can better use it to
shape our learning and so we'll see
better adaptation to the environment
we'll see better mental wellbeing Etc
and there is some uh evidence for that
although with the
caveat
that most of the research that's looked
at what I'm calling arousal coherence
here
we'll pick a autonomic marker so heart
rate pupil dilation something like that
um and then usually it's a emotion that
is used to track so stress anxiety
excitement regardless of veilance some
emotion so there's a slight cavey out
there in the in the
methodological
domain that we're talking about
effective arousal and not emot
exactly but there is quite a a decent
literature now showing that something
like arousal
coherence is linked to better emotional
awareness better self-regulation better
well-being lower anxiety lower
depression lower inflammatory
biomarkers Etc so there is
a there's some research they're pointing
towards this
being potentially the case and I'll I'll
talk about some my empirical stuff which
will come
later um final claim um I mean these two
these last two are not in any particular
order but meta awareness of arousal I
think is a really important concept here
um I'm I'm drawing on the work of sandid
Smith um and their paper of met
awareness or meta control of
attention I think arousal is some
somewhat similarly to attention so it
fits reasonably well but met awareness
of arousal I'm treating as a higher
order monitoring and control over these
lower order arousal processes in
particular so um it this meta awareness
I think will shape the responsiveness of
these lower order sources of
arousal to errors including interceptive
errors ordonomic errors unexpected
conditions in the body
and there's also some evidence that
training this meta awareness of arousal
can increase cerence so
um at Al uh they found that um
meditators had a higher coherence
arousal coherence
so basically sitting with arousal like
during meditation potentially also
during like comatic practices like
having an ice paath or Brea breath work
or things like this and might train the
capacity
to learn about arousal basically rather
than the default regulation strategies
that we might have like
flee um so facilitate learning about
arousal and you have that higher
order uh learning you can also use that
to
regulate um
so if I put all of those claims together
it kind of looks like the figure that we
had in the
paper um again this is not exactly
precise because trying to um present
different levels of temporal depth
within this image I found rather
difficult uh but the basic idea kind of
in the claims autonomic arousal is um
tracking changes in uncertainty and
unexpected changes there can
inform future Precision
estimates above that effective arousal
at I'm I'm saying a higher level of
temporal and Abstract depth effective
arousal um has expectations of
interceptive conditions and also uh
Precision over interceptive conditions
that is determined there uh optimized by
effective arousal and then at a higher
level um meta
arousal can learn about the Precision
waiting errors in effective arousal so
when effective arousal might be uh might
have more noise coming from the
autonomic level for instance so by being
meta aware of your feelings of effective
arousal you may become more aware that
for instance your heart rate is not
matching with your feeling of
stress a simple level
um and
increasing arousal coherence basically
facilitates the information about
changing uncertainty from the autonomic
level up into the conscious
level
um yeah she just returning to the those
basic
claims
um
maybe I have a couple of future
directions um that I'd like to talk
about and we can talk about these more
in a discussion I have I have 50 million
things that I would like to do with this
uh concept and measurement next I'm
really excited because it's so easily
measured um even though there are
methodological
constraints so I'm expecting and and
testing whether arousal coherence is
associated with more adaptive updating
of uncertainty
estimates um the paper by De Burker and
colleagues that I spoke about at the
very beginning the probabilistic
learning paper they have kindly shared
their data with me so been able to have
a look at how coherence might relate to
that I think it's bad form to talk about
results before there written up so maybe
I won't but I um I'll dangle that there
there's there's something with
probabilistic learning um I'm also
looking at how arousal coherence relates
with emotional awareness and
emotional um self-regulation again so
extending on prior work by people like
Sasha selt and Richie Davis um they've
kind of already found these well-being
links but I am wanting to look
specifically if it has to do
with higher order effective like
updating higher order affected
representations and and not getting
stuck um and then another direction
would be that
interventions increasing better
awareness of arousal so mindfulness
homic practices things like ice baths
breath work would lead to increased
arousal
coherence um
excuse me um and basically that
cultivating arousal coherence will help
us to navigate on certainty that's
that's the key we can fill our way
through it
um just two additional things to note um
one this data is readily available
pretty much everywhere so there's
there's so many papers out there that
have looked at uh High arousal emotions
or just affective arousal in conjunction
with some measure of autonomic arousal
across time and some simple linear mix
modeling you can look at arousal
coherence in relationship
to
various indicators which is what I've
done my entire PhD is secondary data um
so if you have some of that data and you
want to look at it let me know and
uh you know actually I think I'll leave
it there because uh the other things I
imagine might come up in the when we
chat anyway while I have a chance just
another opportunity to say thanks to
these Legends it was so delightful to
get to work with Ruben Helen and mark on
my first first Au paper um what a treat
and also two very helpful reviewers who
gave much more feedback and much more
helpful feedback than I had been led to
expect by all the reviewer two
memes and that's
it co thank
you um you could leave the slides up and
yeah let's discuss and if anyone has
questions they can ask and I'll read
it um okay well people are typing their
questions like what led you to study
this intersection of topics for your
PhD uh so I was really interested at the
very beginning of my PhD been quite a
journey about why some people are better
um at dealing with uncertainty than
others I guess you would call it Mee
search um so I started with looking at
When people's worldviews are threatened
and and some people can kind of roll
with that take that on board and then
other people lose their
mind um and I suspected that it had
something to do with embodiment based on
just looking at the people around me who
were better at dealing with
uncertainty
um and then I came across a Carl
friston's work and started looking at
free energy
in particular and and links between I'm
making links in my mind between free
energy and
arousal uh and then for tuly came across
S Summer fils work so these things all
happened within the span of a month
trying to answer this first question and
then received the framework and then
looked at the measurements like God
these really seem to add up together and
so it was just really really nice timing
in terms of the way that I was reading
things
cool yeah I mean I've just been I think
I've just been really lucky about the
the time in my uh in the intellectual
field that I've kind of arrived in
because all of these ideas
are as you might have seen just these
just other people's ideas that I really
like that have just put like this on top
of each other
yeah like the novelty and the speed and
other factors the unifying kind of
spirit make it so that the layering is
very fine and very
fun exactly
exactly um okay so it's a kind of like
reflect how I was seeing it and how you
layered the argument I was thinking
about drinking coffee before
studying and about how that's this kind
of General
pharmacological
intervention and on the first claim you
had one of the pieces of experiment was
about the pharmacological
intervention so it's kind of like it's
an obvious way to think about what these
interventions do but those are entering
the
body and then it's interesting that the
directionality of learning it's like the
natural variation in learning and the
arousal it is happening in the same
pattern as the
intervention would
suggests so in that I kind of like saw
the the bringing together of of
experiments which like in humans or in
any species you can never always have
exactly the
experiment um so that kind of brought
together the idea that the learning
rate is is related to the excitement in
the body um yeah and then that gets very
embodied when again an obvious kind of
corollary of a slower heart rate is more
time in between
pulses
to have high Precision measurements so
there's like a few kind of just very
first past body bases for heart rate and
for pharmaceutical inter itions that
otherwise the connection between like
the body's status and even the learning
rate can feel very abstract when it's
like the least abstrac thing
possible yeah and I think M Allen's work
on that has been really helpful for me
to conceive of that like okay obviously
your brain needs to predict what's going
on in your body so that it can account
for those changes that you your body the
impact that your body has on uncertainty
um another thing that that I've just
been reminded of as you were talking
about the learning rate is
um so I I'm conceiving of this
as like
embodied extend uncertainty processing
extended into the body so predictive
processing is not restricted to the
brain it's a whole it's an organismic
process but that said these things that
we're talking about the different the
changes in
autonomic um States might be represented
also in the likely are represented also
in the brain so not going to make a
claim about necessarily if it's all
brain or if it's also brain and body I
think body but the Locust culus um so
the key source of noradrenaline the
arousal kind of hormone in the brain uh
there was a lovely paper by sales and
colleagues I think it was 2019 where
they showed Locus cus um activity
tracking with Basi and surprise as well
also
linking uh with learning rates so I
think arousal arousal and learning rates
are very
clearly
linked yes okay we're back in the coffee
and the studying and the learning back
in the coffee just have another Sip and
we're we're we're learning through
time hopefully about like how excited or
revved up to be for the learning rate of
the topic that we're studying and then
in figure one the the Precision had this
kind of swoop because it went slowly
down as the coherence increased but then
at the very end it kind of ticked up so
what made you have that little uptick
there or what was that
representing okay so that I um I didn't
mean as much by it as you might have
done by them I'm sorry I was trying to H
with these two these different levels
kind of indicate that these are
different time
scales like I think it could be a um
slip that informative because it could
be it could be a freid and slip on on
the far end of like
synchrony that's also in uninformative
state that's very true yeah
and so it becomes the Precision explodes
so it's kind of like there's one impulse
is to have higher sensory
resolution but
then that is accompanied by um lower
heart rate so lower ability to like do
motor activity so if you're doing long
exercise or something like that like you
you couldn't necessarily just switch on
a dime but then at the slower time scale
you you could relax to have better
sensory acuity but if you're moving fast
it doesn't necessarily matter as much
but then if you're like too coherent
you're like having like a sleepy seizure
or something like
that yeah I think that this is a this is
a really important point and and the
paper kind
of Might gloss over it a little bit um
but with the i in general arousal
coherence I think is a positive
state but not necessarily all the time
so we talk a little bit in there about
how um in certain kinds of processing
like for example in like unrelenting
grief or really acute stress it's
probably more adaptive to turn off the
like to to downweight your inter
receptive signals there and not be
coherent and and for we see um grief and
and suppression are typically associated
with lower coherence so it's not that
it's always for the best um I think this
like capacity of meta
arousal is is likely more important so
being able to adjust whether it's
coherent or not but on average coherence
is a better state
to reside
in or in terms of getting more
information or being able to navigate
uncertainty better but that's not
necessarily what what we always need to
do yeah we just need to be stable and
you know yeah like shock it's kind of
like some something's just stuck and so
the fact that the mutual information
between the body's State and the
cognitive State the mutual information
being low it's not necessarily a bad
thing it's like a mechanism protective
yeah it's a protective and it and it can
be processed later potentially
but um then kind of Mo moving through
the claims getting to where um we have
the the consciously representable
nature of
arousal um and it
isn't arousal
itself that we directly perceive this is
kind of thinking about the interception
as inference because we could have kind
of
a first pass like how excited am I but
then check in and like find out
otherwise or have the biomarkers
otherwise like trying to guess your your
blood pressure so then I thought about
studying with the coffee and a lot of
the things with the pupil which
represents the arousal and then another
I related phenotype with the Cade which
represents the EP syic
value those movements and and muscle
contractions are basically subliminal
most people probably almost all people
cannot
control their even aware of yeah so
there's a layer that is slower than
reading across the
page that we could access and that's
that kind of like
arousal layer so it just is like there's
things that are too
fast like if it were otherwise then we'd
be having a different live stream asking
why we couldn't perceive something else
but in the ways that we have our
attention now um there are things that
are just happening faster that we don't
pay attention to like syntax and letter
recognition and then this is kind of
moving into okay well what is that
slower process that is necessarily
slower and different than the primary
kind of like domain specific
inference I mean I'm thinking of that as
a effect I guess as one instance um I
think there's also an argument to be
made that attention is doing a similar
job
uh yeah have I understood your question
correctly that yeah yeah
yeah just trying to make sense so if
you're thinking about like the lowest
level for example being heartbeat and
then heart rate and
then uh changes in heart rate according
to something at a bigger level I don't
know some other cycle Cadian Rhythm yeah
that's what I was going to ask what is
the arousal and aect nest within and
what does that
mean arousal as in autonomic or arousal
as in affective nested
within because I I treat them as
different okay maybe clarify it then how
do you see yeah sorry I'm thinking of
autonomic arousal as
a lower level inference than effective
but higher level than for instance the
actual
autonomic uh interceptive
inferences so you're a you're inferring
a heartbeat for instance or when you're
heart expecting that and then above that
expecting things like um heart rate or
changes across
time uh and then up at higher levels and
it's not a precise this level this level
um but up above that affective inference
as a kind
of minimal form of metac cognition
including over interceptive information
but not exclusive to interceptive
information um so you can have effective
States even if your interceptive changes
or like autonomic changes are
suppressed and then uh above effective
States I'm imagining the the
metacognition kind of the ACT not
minimal but actual meta awareness of
those of effective arousal
States like knowing that we know those
States or more like an being able to
well both uh being able to actually
report on those States I think is very
different from feeling those States and
the subjective feeling experience which
um PS is talking about as like your your
minimal
Consciousness the feeling of being is a
very different thing from being able to
say what you
feel and self-report on that in my
opinion there's some other people who
agree with me there's probably people
who don't that's
fine uh so um yeah a bit of nesting
nesting nesting is how I'm conceiving of
this and it's not uh by any means
because the modeling hasn't been done I
think it's not a precise this was layer
one this is Layer Two this is layer
three um I just pointing that these
things do appear to be nested within
each
other and of course have a bir
directional
relationship yeah it's very interesting
um a big motivator or I guess kind of
pragmatic implication you said that
having a
better representation that was conscious
whether just naturally like variation in
how well people can self-represent
um or the trainings that that might be
possible like it could be used to shape
our responsivity to the environment and
learning so like what would it look like
or what would that
mean so I think it's the best way to
answer that question I
think uh the simplest way to put it is
that we know the world through our body
like our body is our medium of relating
to the world and so interceptive incits
are necessarily kind of involved with
how we perceive what's going on outside
of
us
um by being kind
of we think about coherence as a kind
of interceptive
accuracy
of changing conditions so you're
integrating it's like an integrative
accuracy
over interceptive conditions or
autonomic
conditions that accuracy
shapes for example
interceptive self inference and the
capacity of the brain to
predict you know the pulsatile blood
flow when that's going to happen over
your eyes so
impact how it adjusts Precision
according to changes that are actually
happening in your body and how well it
can enact those
changes according to the needs of the
environment and by that I
mean changes and uncertainty in the
environment does that Mak sense I'm not
sure if
I rambled a little bit
there like I think it's a
very it's a very
exciting bundle because these are things
these are cycles that we go
through on minute by minute and and day
after
day
and that where that kind of took me and
what reading the paper made me wonder
about was like
entering in that learning example
studying for the from the textbook but
also that could be um a squirrel
learning about the environment or it
could be having a memory of a new
experience so it's not just like a
domain learning but it's like you could
kind of focus attention on the the
primary inference problem like look
harder at the letters so there's a kind
of like attention to the primary
sensory um aspects which on one pass
it's kind of like well that's how you'd
interpret the word better but this is
like suggesting that there's also like a
higher order entry point for improving
our
learning which would be like to be
monitoring our own
awareness and and our embodiment and
like oh that equation made me made my
heart rate increase just to see it or
this is making me sleepy I'm bored this
is making me frustrated like those kinds
of
inferences they're not a waste of time
because they would actually set up the
scaffold
the more adaptive interpretation of the
lower level sensory data but if you just
entered in at the sensory data you might
be missing out on the effective
part yes I agree I think that's a I
think it's a really exciting area for
like looking into in the future because
we can we can test these things you know
we have that capability to test people's
intercept differences for instance um
and like readily available on mobile um
I'm I'm personally quite excited to go
down that pa um and I I agree
that there's a yeah there's something to
be gained from treating feelings as
information across multiple levels and
it's not a new idea obviously so um
there is always this I mean there's been
this idea I think it was Schwarz maybe
uh feelings chor and Steinberg apologies
I'm like I said earlier I don't have
Google but um yeah feeling treating
feelings as information or seeing
feelings as information I think is
really uh valuable and and not yet
explored as much as it could
be yeah we haven't we haven't optimized
that I guess and I I think a few ways in
which the syntheses that you have kind
of though I don't know all the details
of what's been done can maybe go beyond
just saying that there's a correlation
um like the two things that come to mind
is first off it goes beyond saying that
it that emotions or affect or awareness
are
informative because it's not just like
well you could tune into the that stream
or you could tune into the sensory
stream by making them explicitly nested
mechanistically then you can you're you
can learn from both by directionally
like and then a second important piece
is um by connecting it to the biometric
like the heart rate and the variability
and the
pupil then there's a kind of less
emotional entry point like webcams could
report on our pupil acity and our
arcades who knows who already is
tracking that information but then that
gives it gives an entry point that isn't
like asking how one feels which is a
very challenging and involved question
to answer and and and interos around and
some people are terrible at it they
don't
know it's there's big individual
variability and and I guess the point of
my work is like that variability
matters it's informative
how how well you know how you feel or
how well your how you feel lines up with
your body I guess a better way to say
that yeah and that that
variability like within and across
levels it can't be and the goal is not
to like clamp it because we're always
rotating position standing up sitting
down doing all these things that you
can't lock on to value
for which is why the kind of skeleton of
the model is just about how the
variabilities
connect rather than like a number or
like a final kind of
just yeah equation to describe it across
settings yeah I I would like to come up
with some equation
acoss it would be a nice uh future
Direction I think
uh I do think that this kind of thing is
is um possibly usable
for for treatment for assessing the
effectiveness of interventions for
instance um seeing it like basically if
you can tune into your body more through
your
feelings and whether that's valuable um
I would really like to talk about
the um experimental evidence that I
think would
uh back up what I'm talking about more
with the learning external uncertainty
um like yeah maybe I could come back and
talk about that when got a pre when
we've got a preprint I I feel like
uh it's maybe bad for to talk about it
in advance oh it's but it's cool to see
like
how over these even slower slower
timelines
that the research threads can come
together and how they can be brought
together with a lot of the other
technical work that that is out there
and then I think that's sort of the
question that that it's exciting to ask
is like what data sets are already out
there where descriptive statistics can
be done what generative models can be
made and just by what you wrote to
separate things out into what's an
observ a and what's a statistical
relationship like the information is all
there yeah and there's a whole lot more
that haven't T that the reviewers and
collaborators are like please just stop
talking stop talking saying too much um
so there yeah there's a lot that there
is so much literature that kind of fits
into this um framework out there and I
think
is yeah it's exciting it's exciting and
and it's easily
measurable um again with the caveat of
the emotions versus you know and and we
talked about kind of you know
self-reporting on arousal is not
necessarily the same as feeling it so
really trying to work out whether this
difference is happening at the level of
self-report or happening at the level of
feeling in between that and the
interception exactly where that's coming
it's a little bit difficult to pinpoint
because measuring feel ings for instance
is quite difficult in measuring
self-report that may be a different
thing um but that said there's yeah I
I've managed to
I three research papers all pre-existing
data all really interesting topics and
wonderful people who were just willing
to share and collaborate on these so it
looks like this arousal concept relates
with like said um wellbe things and
that's reasonably well established
already but the I guess the key Point um
that I'm going after is the relationship
with navigating uncertainty in the
external
world how that how this relates to that
through through interceptive self-
inference is my affective interceptive
self-
infant is my um my proposal
is there anything else you want to add
or ask or like
mention
um
I am very open to talking about it I
haven't done the modeling I don't have a
mathematics background so uh if anyone
that does wants to talk about it please
hit me up if you have data set if you
have hypotheses you want to talk about
it if you want to see my code it's on
OSF
um yeah that's it just yeah I'm I'm very
keen to talk about it um see if we can I
can take it
somewhere more interesting make it a
little bit more precise make it
usable thanks so much for having me such
a pleasure congratulations on the PHD
and thanks I haven't got it yet almost
almost um almost until next
time until next time I'm looking forward
to it thanks Daniel bye